[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guests are Carl Wagers and
Kansas Hinson call wegers is principal
consultant with process impact a
software Consulting and training company
in Portland Oregon he has a PHD in
organic chemistry Carl is also the
author of 14 books on software
development and other topics his most
recent book is software requirements
Essentials core practices for successful
business analysis and Candace is a
co-author Candace Hinson is a business
architect and PMI AEL certified
practitioner at argon digital a software
development Professional Services and
training company based in Austin Texas
with over 10 years of experience in
product ownership and business analysis
her latest book is software requirement
Essentials core practice in successful
business
analysis Carl and Candace welcome to
software engineering radio today we're
going to talk about software requirement
Essentials and as lot could have it
you've both written a book on that topic
so I'd like to start with A Brief Review
of what requirements and business
analysis mean and spend up to 10 minutes
on five different parts of requirements
engineering actually is requirements
engineering the correct term well I
think it's a slightly optimistic term
but it's the term that I use the term
that's used more often in recent years
for for this domain is business analysis
which encompasses things Beyond just
requirements but requirements
engineering is where my heart's at
excellent so what do we mean when we use
the word requirements who would like to
take that question well I'll start start
with that Gavin and I think this is a
great place to start today because
people interpret the word requirements
in various ways so I always have to
begin my training classes with some
definitions so at least for the the time
we're together during the class we're
all talking about the same kinds of
things so I think of requirements as
encompassing two major perspectives
first there's a description of
stakeholder needs and
constraints and second there's a
description of the capabilities and
characteristics of some solution that
we're trying to build that we expect
will satisfy those needs but people
sometimes talk about requirements as if
they're all one big monolithic kind of
thing I think it's better to put some
adjectives in front of the word
requirements to distinguish these
various sorts of requirements related
information we talk about business
requirements user requirements which are
sometimes generalized to stakeholder
requirements but I don't like that term
very much because as far as I can tell
all requirements come from some
stakeholder there are solution
requirements which are typically
subdivided into functional and
non-functional requirements
non-functional requirements include
things like quality attributes and
constraints we have data requirements
you might talk about features use cases
there's all sorts of things that people
talk about in this domain so I think
it's valuable to to differentiate those
with some adjectives and these various
kinds of information come from multiple
sources at different stages in the life
cycle of your project and they're
represented in a variety of ways thanks
well um try to break them down in the
next sections I think this one is for
Candice what is business analysis cace
oh that's a big question because as Carl
mentioned business analysis is a a
rather large umbrella but in my opinion
at the at the highest level business
analysis is really everything that it
takes to understand of projects or
products or even a companies business
problems and business objectives and
from there Define a solution solution
that would solve that problem or achieve
those objectives from there then
business analysis decomposes that
solution into the set of requirements
knowledge like Carl mentioned that can
be built tested and deployed to meet
those business objectives and solve
those business problems so obviously
that includes a lot of activities and
artifacts and the software requirements
is one piece but a very critical piece
of that thanks and in your book it
discusses 20 requirements practices so
we're not going to be able to cover them
all here but I've picked a good chunk of
them and broken them up to five sections
where we can hopefully spend about 10 15
minutes on each so the first one I have
here is
requirements
elicitation I said that correct yes who
would like to explain what that means
without looking
up well that's another good place for a
definition the first thing we have to do
regarding requirements is to get some
and people often talk about Gathering
requirements ments but that's a little
restrictive the term requirements
elicitation is broader and more accurate
I mean of course there's an aspect of
gathering or collecting requirements out
of people's brains and documents and
existing products and all other sources
but elicitation goes beyond that because
there's also a lot of Discovery and
invention that takes place during
requirements elicitation so you can't
just ask people what their requirements
are and expect to get a useful or very
complete answer
the business analyst is really a guide
or the requirements engineer if we're
being optimistic they're a guide that
leads this requirements
exploration and people also need to
understand that elicitation like the
rest of the stuff that we're talking
about in this General broad category of
requirements development that's an
incremental and iterative process you
can't simply ask people what they want
in some Workshop write it down and then
come back with a good solution sometime
later it would be great if it were that
simple but it's not so we need this
business analyst to guide the process
and try to ask the right sorts of
questions explore the right kinds of
information to get the knowledge that we
need to build a good solution and this
business analyst as a person you just
mentioned well yeah although I keep
getting asked questions about well is AI
going to take our jobs and how is AI
going to affect business analysis and
that's actually something that I haven't
paid much attention to there are other
people doing that but for now yeah it's
people and has this evolved the software
methodology has transitioned from
waterfall to Agile or you know for
example because you mentioned it was an
iter of constant
elicitation well it is and uh even if
you're doing I mean I get really tired
of hearing people talk about waterfall
versus agile as if those are the only
two possibilities and of course they're
not those are two extremes of uh
spectrum and one thing you learn as you
get older is that either terminal
position of a spectrum is almost always
silly and being somewhere in the middle
is almost always more reasonable but but
certainly we don't want to let people
think that you can just do this once at
the beginning of a project go away and
come back later with the right answer
but nor can we just have a couple
conversations as we go along and then
come back for a couple more
conversations and expect to get a a
broad picture of what we're building in
SE the pieces fit together so yeah it's
an ongoing process and partly it's
ongoing because you get some questions
answered you go away and you think about
it and you realize there's more
questions or I didn't fully understand
the answer so I think of requirements
development as Progressive refinement of
details you know you get a certain
amount of information initially and then
you have to elaborate that at the right
time in the right level of detail with
the right participants and so I think
the concepts apply whether you're
talking about a waterfall or or agile
approach or anything in between it's
just a matter of how much you do it and
who's involved and what you do with the
information you get and the Gathering
the requirements is as I understand it
from both sides so the user has a
problem or the business has a problem
you'll try and document that or whatever
it is but then more requirements will
pop up from your side so it's it's
driven from both sides isn't it the
elicitation yeah I can just has got a
lot of experience with those kinds of
vagile projects do you want to talk
about that Candace yeah just a fair as
Carl mentioned it's kind of how you do
it and when you do it you're doing the
elicitation maybe in smaller chunks as
you're preparing for an iteration versus
maybe a whole release but you're still
having to do the same fundamental
activities of getting that information
out of people who may have an idea of
what they want but we still have to
figure out if that's really what they
need if that's going to solve their
problem and then getting that into a
format that can actually be consumed by
the developers so you still have that
iterative and ongoing conversation with
your users with the developers just in
in at least in most agile projects I've
worked on kind of smaller chunks that
leads us on to my next question
perfectly which is do users always know
what solution they need and by the
sounds of it no yeah you know anytime I
see a word like always or never the
answer is almost certainly well not
always there's there's going to be a an
edge case but in this case I would
almost go so far as to say a lot of the
time users don't really know the
solution that they need they may have an
idea or a vision of what they think will
meet their needs but then it takes a
strong and skilled business analyst to
work with their users and understand the
full problem space to say yep that's
really going to be a correct solution to
meet your problem or yeah that looks
shiny or sounds good but it's not really
going to do what you think it will do
and so as Carl talked a little bit about
you know eliciting and getting
information out of people one of the
ways we like to do this is by asking
about usage like what are the things you
need to do today to get your job done
and then we can help translate that into
what it might look like in the
future yeah because I've always wondered
could companies bring a product onto the
market for the first time take for
example apple or someone it's brand new
it's been
invented where are the requirements
coming from there must be some problem
space they're trying to address or if
it's brand new in the market is it just
better than what was there before or
it's a strange
one yeah and consumer products
definitely are more likely trying to
exploit opportunities and they see a a
niche maybe where some maybe even
unspoken or like we didn't know we
needed iPhones or smartphones until they
existed that was exactly my my thought P
there and now we can't live without them
and so in that case it was probably a in
case of Apple just being smart and
saying hey people have cell phones to
today we can make them better there's an
opportunity we could be the first to
Market and because they were I mean it
really took off Candice touched on a
really important point there that I want
to emphasize Gavin she mentioned usage
and that's one of my hot button issues
when it comes to requirements is that
you can take two approaches to exploring
requirements one is to to focus on the
product you know ask people what
features do you want the other is to
focus on usage ask people what they need
to do with it as Candice brought up and
I think that is an absolutely essential
point and I think that would be
applicable certainly to not just
business situations where we can talk
about how people do their job now and
how that might be different but you can
do that with new product development
where we think not in terms of the
features that somebody might say oh
that's cool or you put it in because
someone figured out how to do it and
perhaps someone will find it useful sure
some of that's fine but let's think
about what people want to do with a
device and as Candace mentioned they may
not even know they want to do that but
let's try to imagine how that might work
think about what people would do if they
had this product available and I believe
that in almost every case a focus on
usage is more likely to yield accurate
and valuable understanding of
requirements than is a focus on products
and their
features yeah that was one one of my
next questions about the the users
always know what they want to do with it
versus what the solution is they need so
thanks for that what information do we
need first I think there's a nice
chapter in your book called laying the
foundation which I've kind of skipped
over but obviously we need to do that
can you take us through that yeah I can
comment on that we do have six sections
of practices these 20 practices are
grouped into six categories five of them
address the major subdivisions of
requirements engineering that is
elicitation analysis specification
validation and management which I think
we'll get to today but we also have this
this chapter called laying the
foundation because we describe five
practices that I think are fundamental
to putting into place the basics upfront
about what we need to do to understand
how to proceed with the rest of the
project so the first practice really
addresses this question of let's make
sure we all understand the problem
before we Converge on any particular
solution next let's define our business
objectives so the participants all
understand why we're even undertaking
this
project it's important also to define
the solutions boundaries which helps the
team take scoping decisions what's in
what's out we can't do everything so
let's draw those lines so all of that
will then help you identify and
characterize the various stakeholders
who need to contribute to the
requirements process and little safety
tip there are almost certainly a lot
more stakeholders than you think there
are initially so that that's worth
thinking about and finally from those
stakeholders we can then identify the
empowered decision makers who are going
to have to handle the various types of
many requirements related decisions
they're going to encounter and and let's
figure out who those people are and how
they're going to make decisions
preferably before they encounter their
first major decision yeah I think we
touched upon some of this when we last
spoke so just for the listeners that
haven't heard that show episode 518 when
we spoke on more General software
engineering lessons based on your 50
years experience of that
time excellent so we're going to dig
into the five terms you
mentioned requirement solicitation is
what we're almost finished analysis
requirement specification validation and
management before we move on to the next
section I'd like to pick an example that
we can pull apart as we move
forward would either of you be able to
give me an example project we could talk
about for requirements analysis our next
section
sure so this is a project I worked on
several years ago we were completely
rebuilding one of our clients credit
adjudication platform so how they get
information from customers go to credit
bureaus determine if someone is credit
worthy and then give them a decision so
we had set the scope of doing kind of a
major re-platform of their credit
adjudication process to make it more
flexible going forward and to do that we
had to make major database schemes
changes and so we can talk about this
through the various areas today as well
but in terms of elicitation and kind of
understanding the problems one big
hurdle we ran into close to launch was
we had to make these these large
database schema changes to support our
project and probably a couple weeks
before our goli date our main
stakeholder came and said no we couldn't
change the database schema if we had
just taken her at face value this would
have completely derailed our project and
sent us back to square one in terms of
defining what to do so instead of just
saying yep let's start over again I
worked with her did some licitation to
understand why she was so resistant to
changing the database schema well as it
turned out she had several kind of SQL
queries that she had written based on
the database that were driving all of
her regulatory reporting so once we knew
this instead of going back to square one
we actually offered to rewrite all of
the SQL queries so that her reporting
would work with the new database
structure so we could launch on time and
thus we saved that that project at least
at that point and we were able to move
forward so we can continue to talk about
that one as we go excellent and I guess
it it does come down to how flexible
they are on that yes or no doesn't
it if she said no I'm not I'm not going
any further into detail then there's not
lot you can do is that there's two
points well there's a lot of good stuff
in what Candace just said but there are
two points I wanted to rein en Force One
is the nature of constraints we talk a
lot about requirements but we also get
constraints from our various
stakeholders that we have to understand
and and document and communicate to all
the other participants because those
limit some of the choices that we can
make either in terms of what
requirements we can do or what the
designers and developers can do and in
this case saying no you can't touch the
database that's a pretty major
constraint in this case it could have
been a showstopper constraint but we
need to know about those things and the
second point I want to make is that
Candace mentioned that she asked why and
that's a wonderful question to ask
especially if you hear something that
kind of surprises you or sounds like
it's maybe going to limit what we need
to do let's understand why because you
people like to say well the customer is
always right so we have to do what they
want and that's just silly we all know
the customer is not always right but the
customer always has a point so we have
to understand and respect that point and
then figure out what to do moving
forward and you mentioned blockers or
showstoppers there constraints the two
usual ones are time and money aren't
they with regards to business yeah those
are project level constraints and then
there can be requirements level of
constraints there are lots of kinds of
constraints we should probably put some
adjectives in front of those
too okay so I'm going to move us on to
requirements analysis who would like to
explain what that is can take a shot at
that uh you know in a way I I used to
think requirements analysis just sounded
like something that just somehow happens
if you stare at the requirements long
enough but in reality there are some
specific things we can do around
requirements to fully understand the the
requirements that we have that's all
really what analysis is about so
requirements analysis involves first
ensuring that the needs of all the
stakeholders are understood and
documented appropriately and the outcome
of this a successful analysis gives us
confidence that we can build a
satisfactory solution to meet those
needs we can Define it we can agree upon
it we can build it and we can test it so
there are a lot of things to look for
when you're analyzing requirements for
example we need to understand each
requirements origin and rationale that
gets back to why again so why is this in
there and there can be a lot of reasons
and some of them are good some maybe
mean oh I guess we don't need to do that
a big part of analysis involves
decomposing requirements into
appropriate levels of detail and then
deriving requirements from other
information such as business rules or
policies those aren't requirements but
they can certainly turn into a lot of
requirements I mean just think about
security you can have a very concise
security requirement but that turns into
a whole lot of
functionality we need to make sure that
any exceptions that could take place are
identified they're handled we need to
Define except criteria and so forth so
there's a lot to think about besides
just writing down each requirement as
clearly as you can analysis goes down to
another level and you talk about once
the analysis is ongoing or complete ter
term requirements sets could you take us
through that yeah there's a list of
requirements and a a business analyst
can find many potential problems by
looking at individual requirements and
isolation I've kind of done that as a
consultant over the years I've reviewed
a whole lot of requirements documents
for clients and I can find a lot of
problems just by looking at a specific
requirement you can find ambiguities and
and things like that that that let you
know that maybe there's a need for more
work on it but requirements don't exist
in isolation they exist in the context
of lots of other requirements so that's
what I mean by a set of requirements and
when you're analyzing sets of related
requirements you have to look for some
different things you need to look for
omissions is there a requirement missing
from this set of related things or is
there a piece of information missing
from certain requirements look for
conflicts and inconsistencies you can
have a parent requirement that conflicts
with its children or you can have one
requirement that says do a and the other
one says do B but you can't logically do
both look for duplications that's a
whole conversation in itself there are
dependencies One requirement might have
on another and please keep in mind when
we're talking about this general term
requirement here I don't really care
what kind of information you're using on
your project you might be using user
stories as your atom of
requirements but that user story could
have dependencies on others as well so
if you don't like the word requirement
for your project then substitute you
know whatever term globally this is your
local terminology priorities are
relative you you can look at One
requirement and say well that's you know
high priority or X priority but that's
relative statement compared to what
compared to the others in the set and so
forth missing requirements incidentally
are perhaps the hardest kind of Errors
to find because they're not there
they're invisible so they're kind of
hard to see so these are some of the
things you look for if you're trying to
analyze a set of related requirements
and Candace when you spoke about the
database schema and the user or the
business needing it for compliance
reasons there be quite a few parts and
pieces of data that would needed to be
set together or kept together so that
would sort of feedback to this wouldn't
it once you said we'll rewrite these
queries but we need to keep x y and Zed
together absolutely yeah in terms of the
requirements set we had the the features
that described the changes to the
database schema and so we relied heavily
on that when we were analyzing the SQL
queries to rewrite them and um what are
requirement
models oh one of my favorite things
so requirement models are just really
any way to visually represent
requirements information a lot of people
when we talk about requirements use
natural language text but a lot of times
that's not the best way to represent
information so these could be tables
pictures wireframes or even models we're
familiar with from say a uml type
modeling language like process flows or
data flow diagrams but they can be
really helpful in finding requirements
and identifying those gaps in your
requirements that Carl mentioned in
terms of things you were looking for in
that requirement set I've also found
it's a really great tool for licitation
as well it's an interesting
psychological aspect of humanity that
we're much quicker to correct something
if when we're shown something than to be
able to make something out of nothing so
if we have those requirements models
that show a view of the world then our
stakeholders can tell us if they are
correct or not and how would you create
those models just sketch p and paper or
are you know it really depends on what
you trying what information you are
trying to show visually so I'm a big fan
we use Lucid chart here at argon digital
for our more formal models for
wireframes certainly just as a sketch
pad back in the days when we got to be
in person I love just moving sticky
sticky notes on a whiteboard yeah it's
surprisingly effective isn't it yep
because it's very you can move them
around if it's wrong it's not set in
stone and then you can take a picture of
it and kind of more formalize it later
and so so it's just really powerful to
get that information out of people as
well as to do that analysis and one of
the things I recently found out I guess
a couple years ago is that not everybody
thinks the same way I mean it sounds
obvious but until you actually think
about it you grow up thinking everybody
thinks like you and this was true for
myself as well I realized a couple years
ago that I have aphantasia which is the
inability to see pictures in my head I
just kind of assumed nobody could see
pictures in their head but I was wrong
and so for me Lear learning that and
kind of helped turn the light bulb of
why I love visual models so much because
I can see it in person so to speak right
on the screen or in paper or on the
Whiteboard versus trying to visualize it
in my head interesting thank you I'm a
big fan of modeling as well I took a a
course in structured analysis and design
many years ago 1986 I think and that
just totally transformed how I thought
about software development tremendously
powerful tools they are lots of kinds of
pictures we can draw standard diagrams
from these various modeling languages
like uml or structured analysis or I
zero and there's a lot of them and one
thing I always recommend to people is
please do not invent your own modeling
notation because these are communication
tools it's a language and we all have to
be able to speak and read the same
language if we're going to communicate
effectively if you draw some kind of
picture and nobody knows what an arrow
with two double-head arrows me means
then it's going to be a problem so
there's lots of standard kinds of models
we should learn about them this should
be a standard practice for every
business analyst and I suggest that they
use the standard models in almost every
case because I think it will be quite
rare that they want to depict some
information and nobody has yet figured
out a picture to draw for that and um
with regards to this section of
requirements analysis can you give me an
example when this step is not needed or
is it something that is always needed so
I believe that no matter what project or
product you're working on some level of
requirements analysis is necessary now
the level how much analysis you do and
whether you're using specific visual
models or whether you're creating
prototypes versus I've done this a
thousand times so I'm able to do the
analysis ad hoc in my head that could
definitely vary but I think you are
still doing some level of analysis for
every single requirement that we are
writing now some cases where you might
use less analysis might be if the
product or product team are well
established and they have you know
consistent delivery velocity so maybe
then you're using less time on analysis
but you're still doing some on the other
hand if you're doing new or risky or
unknown projects or unknown features
you're going to spend a lot more time on
analysis to really understand that
problem space and in those
situations they might call for a
prototype because it's brand new
absolutely especially if you're building
something that that doesn't exist
prototypes are a great way to kind of
get that that early in iterative
feedback by putting something in front
of users that they can either imagine
themselves interacting with or in some
cases actually interact with so
absolutely prototypes should at least be
considered on all of the projects this
point as well because that would also
give you U more requirements questions
to ask the the users of the business
once you try to build a thing exactly
for your example kind of to do you need
to do a prototype or is it
more because this one was more API it
was more backend it was it was all
automated we didn't have as many
prototypes but we did have a simple UI
where the users would view information
and be able to reprocess different
adjudications and so for that case we
did have a very kind of simple wireframe
prototype that we used in our early
analysis yeah because some prototype is
something that you can throw away
sometimes sometimes it grows into the
product you just have to make sure you
understand up front what are we going to
do with this prototype are we going to
use it to gain knowledge and then throw
it away and build the real thing or are
we going to use it as a starting point
which will evolve into the product the
strategy that you take with those two
scenarios is very different because if
it's the ladder where you expect it to
become the product you better build it
with production quality code from day
one instead of getting into a situation
where someone says wow this looks great
I think you're done can we have this and
the intent was not to do that and then
you have a problem when would that
decision be made but you when you start
that prototype whether it's going to be
threw away or well I would do that at
that point because I think of a
prototype as being an experiment you're
taking a tentative step into the
solution space saying if we understand
the requirements correctly then here's a
way we might approach building it or
maybe you know that you don't understand
the requirements thoroughly and so you
build the prototype to help you explore
those further and plug gaps in your
knowledge so view it as an experiment
and understand what your objective is
you know how will you determine if the
Prototype has served its purpose and
that thought process should let you
decide okay what do we do with it when
we're done excellent so I'm going to
move us on to our third section
requirements
specification now the word specification
for me I think of like rfc's request for
comments or some big hideous massive
thing that tells you how to do exactly
everything is that what we mean well you
could and in certain situations you need
that kind of information because if
you're going to be mailing your
requirements off to some offshore
development company to uh build it
they're going to have fewer
opportunities perhaps for day-to-day
quick responses to questions and
clarifications and and elaborations and
they need more more details really boils
down like so many things here to a
question of risk and I think when people
look at these books that talk about
requirements it can be a little
overwhelming 10 years ago I wrote the
Third Edition of my book software
requirements which was co-authored with
joy batty and that turned out to be a
rather large book it's about 645 pages
long but that doesn't mean you have to
do all that stuff what you need to do is
say here's a bunch of tools and
techniques and practices and we will use
whichever of those in whatever level of
detail and timing is necessary to manage
the risk on our project and the risk
we're concerned about is either building
the wrong solution entirely or having to
do a lot of rework to then fix whatever
solution you have or whatever partial
solution I hate rework I hate unplanned
rework doing over something that we've
already done so I think people need to
keep in mind mind the question of how
far wrong could we go with this if we
don't do analysis or if we don't write
down our requirements and some
structured way to communicate to other
people so I think requirement
specification is really important but we
should remember it has two meanings
first it refers to the process of
recording what you learn about
requirements in some persistent and
sharable form and then the second sense
is the term which is what I think you
were thinking of Gavin is whatever
container you store that requirements
knowledge in it could be big it could be
small different problems require
different approaches and it doesn't have
to be a document could be a document or
a spreadsheet or a database or a
commercial requirements management tool
or a bunch of sticky notes on the wall
whatever works for your team but we've
got different kinds of information that
we need to record and I think it's
important to do that simply to ensure
effective communication both among the
various stakeholders and across time
human memories are imperfect and
incomplete they fade and distort over
time and strangely other people cannot
yet access them so I think of a
requirement specification in some form
serving as a persistent group memory for
this critical requirements
knowledge yeah it's an agreed way to
document and communicate right just a
note for the listeners car mentioned a
book that he did 10 years ago we also
did a show 15 years ago very early one
episode 114 with Kristoff Ebert on
requirements engineering so once you
finish this it'll be good to listen to
that one after and see how far we've
come
along okay so I think we've covered off
my next question which is how formal is
this specification which is kind of
because my misunderstanding of the term
yeah that that's worth elaborating on
just a second if I could Gavin is it you
know how formal it is and the answer is
the same as unfortunately with so many
questions around software is well it
depends it should be exactly as
comprehensive and formal as it needs to
be to manage those risks of having to do
a bunch of rework because because we got
it wrong it's easy to go wrong in either
direction of formality and
comprehensiveness you can try to pin
down every requirement in detail up
front you know in the classic although I
think rarely practiced in reality
waterfall approach or you can rely on
telepathy Clairvoyance and memories
instead of writing anything down and
both of those approaches are likely
doomed to fail so let's use some of the
the things that kind of Candace was
getting at you know how complex the
problem is how long it goes on and that
sort of thing to try to determine well
how much effort should we put into
recording this versus just saying okay I
think I know what you mean I'll call you
when I'm done so we've answered the
question how formal is this it depends
and also what the specification looks
like this isn't an rfcd format this is
just what works for the project and also
what you touched upon there Carl um
about how detailed the
specification needs to be potentially
goes back to what you said before with
the limits of time and money you know
you don't want to spend the whole
project trying to document the project
so kind of with your example project
what was your agreed way to document and
communicate you know under the term
specification so I actually had worked
with this client for a lot of their
projects to set up how they would kind
of structure their requirements and
requirement specification so we were
using a modified safe or scaled agile
approach so we organized our
requirements into epics and features
down to the user stories that the
developers would Implement in in their
iterations and then we would group those
together into the releases and we were
using a requirements management tool at
that time to organize everything and so
that was a really great way because it
had it was a centralized repository
everybody could access it it had a
really robust version history so we
could tell if someone tried to change
our requirements which happened from
time to time however one of the things
we did find is that like most
requirements tools or even some
specifications they tend to be point in
time so this was the user story when we
developed it but that requirements
management tool won't tell you we built
that in Sprint one but that was changed
by another story in Sprint 3 or a bug
that happened later so I've been a
really big fan actually for my civil and
Structural Engineering days something
called an asilt so it's kind of some
lightweight documentation that says at
the end of the release what do we
actually deploy what is the product as
built in in use versus the Myriad of
stories that we built to support that
release so you used a tool requirements
Gathering tool just for the listeners is
that commer thing open source thing or
Google doc there are many many
requirements management Tools in fact
archon digital has done I think two tool
studies of I think up to a hundred
different requirements management tools
that exist in the marketplace oh if
you've got some links I'll put them in
the show notes uh yeah I can dig those
up some of them are commercially
available some of them are open source
and some of them cost a lot of money in
this case we were using uh Microsoft's
Azure product their requirements
management tool but there are many
others J
rally I can't even rattle off all of the
different tools that exist out there
thank you and I guess from what you were
saying Carl where they agreed upon way
to communicate document the
specification isn't applicable to only
large teams or large
companies no not at all I don't know if
you've ever had an experience like this
but I worked on a project once many
years ago there were just three of us on
the project I was leading it and and I
was doing the requirements which were
fairly informal we didn't have uh
anything as structured as what Candace
was describing this was in the oh gez
mid 1980s before I really appreciated
how important this was and we would have
a weekly meeting and then we'd go off
and and work on what we agreed to work
on for the week and we'd come back and
uh reconvene to continue and on two
occasions we walked away the three of us
from a meeting with different
understandings of what we had decided to
do and so we worked in different
directions for that next week and that
that didn't really work out very well so
even having rudimentary recording of the
knowledge and the decisions that are
made I think is really important because
people's memories simply are not as
reliable as Everyone likes to think they
are have you ever had a conversation
where some decision was made or
agreement was reached and people walked
away and you found out later that they
had different understandings of those
decisions or agreements yeah I was just
trying to think of whether a tool like
GitHub issues would be suitable to do
this but when you do an issue or this is
what we're trying to do it often doesn't
capture the why which is which is what I
think you're saying is why did we get to
that point or how did we and then if all
three of you are have a different memory
of why that decision was made or even
what the decision was yeah um yeah
that's happened a lot cuz it goes back
to the initial or the the ongoing sorry
requirements capturing of yeah we've got
to do this but but why you know why did
you think we did it that way and when
was that agreed to change it right so
having some records like that I think is
very valuable it doesn't have to be
again any more detailed than necessary
but I like this phrase a persistent
group memory which can then be a
resource that everybody can go to is a
going to be complete and perfect and
current all the time no probably not and
it takes some effort but it probably
takes less effort to build and maintain
that repository of knowledge decisions
and and agreements and details than it
does to build something found out you
did it wrong and then build it
again well let's just move on to the
next section because I think it feels
fits nicely so requirements validation
is the next section how do you validate
what what you're doing basically is that
is that correct what does that mean
candas well I can maybe talk a little
bit about what validation means and then
i' I'd love to hear how Candace's team
did that on their project uh you know
just because you've accumulated some set
of requirements in in any form whether
it's telepathy or whether it's detailed
in a a tool that doesn't necessarily
mean you've got the right requirements
uh you could have a set of beautifully
written and modeled requirements that
seem crystal clear complete and
unambiguous and yet they could still be
wrong wrong in the sense that they do
not completely satisfy the need that
we're trying to do with our solution so
we need to validate requirements to make
sure that the specified solution would
satisfy the real business needs and
hopefully achieve the intended outcomes
that the stakeholders are looking for I
think it's a lot cheaper to do that
before you finish building the product
and then ask the users if you got it
right so we want to look for for
techniques that can give us that
validating information that we're on the
right track all along the
way and can you give me an example of
that
validation absolutely yeah so I mean
when we're validating the requirements a
a lot of what at least my goal is to get
as many eyes on the requirements as
possible to have different people with
different lenses look at the
requirements and compare them to other
requirements information whether that be
prototypes or visual models or even a
solution architecture to to find issues
to say will this actually meet our
business objectives and solve our
business problems and so reviewing
requirements can be as simple as just
reading them and saying hey do you have
the same understanding as I do to as
formal as an inspection with checklist
of specific things to look for but I
love getting multiple people to to
review my requirements in the case of my
project we were constant LLY reviewing
requirements as because we were we were
sprinting in an agile is fashion so we
were reviewing requirements with my the
developers and testers or as Carl likes
to call them the victims of our
requirements so I was weekly reviewing
my requirements with them I was also
reviewing with our solution Architects
to ensure that what we were defining
would actually meet our intended goal
because we did understand what the
business problems were up front which is
a really you know foundational piece to
understand because if you don't
understand what problem you're solving
how do you know if your requirements
will meet that problem or solve that
problem and then of course with my
business stakeholder as well reviewing
both the high level requirements to make
sure that the problem was solved and
then also some of the lower level
requirements of the details of how we
would get to that final
state so that was one way we validated
them in this case I didn't yet know
about testing the requirements that was
one of my eye openers as I was
co-authoring with Carl was how we can
use our multiple views of requirements
information like visual models and text
based requirements to test the
requirements before you've written any
code at all so we didn't do that on this
project but it's a valuable tool that I
will and now currently do use on my
current projects and it's really about
having two different thought processes
so either requirements and testing and
in two different brains if it can be and
comparing them to find issues in both
issues in requirements and issues in
tests can you test your requirements are
are met software absolutely and people I
think are surprised to think about that
but that was another real eye opener for
me you know as we go through our careers
you have a a handful of of small
experiences and you realize there's a
really powerful message in there and the
very first time that I did that that
message came through I had written some
requirements for a project and it was
just you know a couple dozen
requirements it was a simple thing but
then I said said well I wonder how I
could tell if these requirements had
been correctly implemented and so I
wrote down a bunch of tests to go along
with those so as Candace said really
there are two different thought
processes one is describing go build
this and the other is describing how do
we tell if we built the right thing
correctly which is really both
validation and verification so then I
took this set of requirements and a set
of tests and I mapped them against each
other and I made sure that every test
could be executed by firing off certain
set of requirements and I made sure that
every requirement was covered by one or
more tests and every single time I did
that in my career I found errors I found
maybe a place where there was some test
that couldn't be executed well what does
that mean it means either I'm missing or
have some incorrect requirements that
would let that test happen or it means
the test is inv valid and I don't know
which is which but the fact that we
created multiple views multiple
representations of that knowledge a set
of written requirements and a set of
written tests and even better you could
have a prototype you could have some
models like Candace talked about in
other words multiple representations of
the knowledge then give you the
opportunity to compare them this way you
can take a diagram and some tests and
Trace through it with a highlighter pen
and you can find errors that way when
you hit a test and your picture doesn't
let you do it okay something's wrong and
here's an important point
if you only create one representation of
requirements and it doesn't matter what
that is whether it's just stories or
just acceptance criteria or just
pictures if you create only one
representation you must believe it it's
all you have but if you create more than
one particularly if different people
create them then you can compare them
you can find these disconnects and
errors and incorrect or different
assumptions people made so I think
that's an enormously powerful way to
improve the quality of requirements
early on and if you're doing that in
conjunction with the people who have the
needs that helps you validate that those
requirements you end up with will meet
their needs and is there something that
this validation you mentioned validation
and verification are they the same thing
well they aren't really the same thing
although the terms are frequently
confused a team can make F make sure
that their code passes its unit
integration and system some tests they
can confirm that the code correctly
implements the design they can confirm
that the design addresses all of the
requirements those are all software
verification activities but they still
don't tell you if the requirements are
the right solution requirements or not
that's what validation about so kind of
the colloquial way people say that is
that verification checks to see that you
did something right validation checks to
see that you did the right thing when
you get to the very top level of
requirements then basically they're the
same thing because you're validating
against what someone told you or what
you found in various documents you know
whatever the source of the requirements
is that's how you validate you have to
go back to the source and that's
essentially verifying that you've done
that translation correctly as well but
but basically validation and
verification are complimentary they are
not the
same so if you've got your
requirement that could be feature
X you've done that feature you've
written the most applicable tests for it
unit tests property based tests
integration test what have you does that
not mean because your tests are passing
and the features been implemented that
you validated the requirements and it's
soorry you verified and now it's valid
or is this a step completely regardless
to what the features you've
developed if I asked that correctly
ideally you'd be validating that they
are the right features to build before
you build them so the way I think of it
is that we should be validating before
we build and then we verify after we
build to say did we build it correctly
so some of the colloquialisms that we
like to use is did we build the right
thing or did we build the thing
correctly and so building the right
thing is validation building it
correctly is verification and I actually
sometimes when I teach my training
classes go back to a story again from my
civil structural engineering days you
know when a bridge fails it's all over
the news and and one of the first
questions is well was it built to the
specification so verification or was it
designed Wrong by the engineer and that
designing wrong is more of that
validation of like did we actually
confirm that it would withstand the
loads that we needed it to withstand
versus did I lay the rebar on that
bridge at 8 in intervals as per the
specification uh or you know use the
right thickness of Bolt or
whatever okay I think I understand that
right I was more trying to pull part
what Carl was saying where we've got
this software based Suite that validates
and verifies our
requirements and is that the same as the
test we already write for software or is
this something new I'm not sure what you
mean software based Suite of tests like
your your test Suite where you've
implemented a feature or your test in a
small unit of code they if you scoop
them all up because they've been driven
by a requirement to create this thing
does that not mean the requirement is
then satisfied or no not well it means
the requirement is satisfied but it
doesn't tell you if it was the right
requirement it doesn't mean the customer
satisfied or the business need is
satisfied so that Gap there that that's
the Gap right that's exactly the
difference between validation and and
verification and I think Candice
explained it nicely but yes you can you
can run all those tests you can say but
wait wait a minute I satisfied the
specification so I don't know what
you're complaining about it's like well
because you're missing a whole chunk of
stuff we need or you misinterpreted what
I said or or things have changed you
know that's the difference between
validation and verification than you so
I'm going to take us on to the last part
of our show which is requirements
management so who would like to explain
this I'll start Candace has got a lot of
uh experience that she can fill in some
details but so you know so far we 've
been talking primarily about
requirements development activities you
know these four domains of elicitation
analysis specification and validation
and most of our practices are in those
categories and the large volume of any
book on requirements or business
analysis covers those kinds of
activities but requirements management
is the subdomain of requirements
engineering that deals with how the
requirements are used on the project and
how the project responds to Evol
involving needs um there are several
valuable requirements management
practices they include things like
Version Control of requirements as they
change over time because we want to keep
track of those changes sometimes you
have to revert to an earlier version and
it's good to know why a requirement was
changed we want to track requirement
status as each one of them again a
requirement being whatever granularity
you're at user stories are fine but we
want to track status as they move from
being proposed through whatever steps in
their life cycle exist until ultimately
it's either delivered and verified in
the product or perhaps deleted from the
the base or deferred to a future release
requirements traceability or tracing
that's another important practice and
you know if we had written a book about
the 21 most important business analysis
practices I think traceability would
have been the one we'd added but we left
that out I think most teams probably
don't do do much tracing other than
perhaps some requirements to tests and
again that's a risk-based thing I talked
to uh a guy once the very first course I
taught on requirements and I've taught
about 250 of them now but the very first
one I taught around 1995 there was a guy
in the class who had worked on the
Boeing trip 7 airplane project and he
said their requirement specification for
the software was a stack of paper six
feet thick and they had a complete
requirement tracebility Matrix and for
an airplane that's a pretty good idea
but most people aren't going to do
something that rigorous for you know a
phone app or something but the two
requirements management practices that
we talk about in the book and that do
apply to every project are establishing
and managing requirements baselines and
then of course managing changes to
requirements effectively so those are I
think core parts of requirements
management that apply to everyone and
what's a requirements
Baseline sure I can take that that one
so a requirements Baseline is really any
set of scope that has been agreed by the
stakeholders development and testing to
be developed tested and deployed as a
group and once they have that alignment
this kicks off the Change Control
process this you know managing the
changes after it has been aligned
there's a couple of different types of
baselines that we talk about so they can
be time bound where you start with a
time box like a increment a set of
increments or release and then you know
when you're going to deploy so you fill
up that time box up to your development
and testing capacity and that becomes
your Baseline alternatively we also have
scope bound baselines so we don't know
the deployment date yet because we
haven't necessarily sized everything but
we take a logical group set of
functionality and we agree that it can
be developed tested and deployed
together regardless of which type of
Baseline you're using it it's really
used to align all the parties that that
we can start and move forward with
development with minimal risk of major
changes I mean change always happens but
we don't want to get halfway through and
find out we've built completely the
wrong thing so getting that Baseline
says yep we acknowledge there will be
changes but we are confident enough that
we can build this and that the changes
will be relatively minor and that does
of course officially start the Change
Control process for that set of scope so
really a baseline is simply an agreement
you know what we're going to build in a
particular chunk of time or chunk of
work and that's a pretty good idea to
have explicit even if it has some
opportunities for changing is there an
example you have from your project
Candace where you said we agreed to get
XY said done but the user customer came
back and said nah we need this done and
you got to deal with it so we we
definitely had changes on our project we
had a kind of a multi-tiered approach to
our baselines since we were doing a
modified scaled agile approach in scaled
agile they have program increments so
they all the teams that are working on
similar products form an Agile Release
Train and they agree to a release
schedule which is typically four to six
iterations that's a program increment
and during that program increment
they'll have a planning session where
they establish the Baseline for that
program increment or release and so we
would established baselines at that
level which was again typically four to
six iterations so roughly a quarter and
then as well at the iteration level so
every every Sprint or iteration during
Sprint planning we would also have the
Baseline of this is what is in scope for
this Sprint versus the other Sprints and
having that multi-tiered Baseline meant
that I as the product owner could move
things between iterations as long as I
kept them in the same release Baseline
now of course you mentioned if the
stakeholder comes back and says no we
need you know something else well that's
part of that Change Control process so
we would be able to take those in
assess the change and depending on our
capacity could say yes we can either do
that or we can but what are the
tradeoffs what do we take out of the
release or the iteration so that we can
bring in the new story that you're
asking for and that process doesn't have
to be super onerous um it can be you
know fairly lightweight involving you
know emails and discussions but every
team should know how they request
changes and how those changes get
incorporated into their products so that
so they're all aligned effectively right
one of the things Carl likes to talk
about is that requirements is a
Communications um problem or
communications project so to speak it's
not really a technical issue it's really
can we get everybody aligned on what we
should be building and track that over
time how do you manage these changes
that they ask for just in the agreed
requirement specification that we've
discussed about or is there a different
way so we had kind of a very lightweight
Change Control process that we had
agreed upon where as changes were
identified they would get sent usually
via email sometimes through like a
Communications IM tool like slack and
then we would put those in our
requirements management tool so any
requirement whether it was part of the
initial specification or part of the
chain Change Control process would get
entered into our requirements management
tools so that we had one place to track
everything from there we would assess
kind of the impact of that change so how
big it was we would size it with the
team and the development and testing
team and from there we'd kind of talk
about the urgency so is it something
that needed to be in the current release
or could it wait for a future release if
it was for the future release it just
got put in the backlog if needed to be
part of that current release then we
would talk about trade-offs do we need
to remove something from this release to
make room for this if the trade-offs
were acceptable then we would move the
impacted scope out bring the new change
in and it would be move through the
development cycle in the requirements
management tool so this was pretty
lightweight we didn't have a whole lot
of approvals but we did have you know a
couple of checkpoints to say we have to
do all of our requirements development
work with changes just like normal
requirements so we have to elicit
analyze um specify and validate them so
we did we did all of that and to under
you know ensure that we had the right
requirements documented as part of the
change and then once we knew the impacts
then we had another kind of check point
to
say is this higher priority than what
we're working on now so that we can make
the appropriate trade-offs and you know
keep the release moving so in that way
we were able to take in most changes and
just have that open communication there
a few toggles you can switches you can
tweak depending on what the the user's
after and see if it messes up your
Baseline excellent so I guess it sounds
like the requirements tools are separate
from your project tools it this isn't
the same as traditional project man
management at all is it well I always
kind of uh wonder what's what people are
thinking about when they talk about
traditional anything it somehow sounds
pejorative like anything traditional is
old-fashioned and therefore useless or
bad you know sometimes people will think
oh we're agile around here we don't do
traditional project management or
traditional Fillin the blank but it's
much more important to consider whether
a certain practices likely to increase
the Project's chance of success
regardless of whether that practice is
brand new or whether it's been used for
decades so for example all projects
Define requirements baselines as Candice
described it whether they call them that
are not it's just an agreement about
what we're going to implement in a
certain period of time or a certain
release people do that although they may
not think in terms of a Baseline and
then if you say well you know here you
ought to have baselines they think oh
well that that's oldfashioned you know
we don't do baselines yeah you are
you're just not calling them that you
may be calling it an iteration plan or
something well I had in my head was
traditional being a Gant chart that you
move stuff around on and and you know
that's you still do that I mean people
are still doing tasks on any project
they're still doing them in a certain
sequence they're estimating how long
those tasks are going to take they're
looking at dependencies between tasks
that have to be done in a certain order
you know this has to be finished before
I can finish that a Gant chart's a
convenient way to show that and you
maybe find people that say well you know
that's traditional that's old we don't
do that but you're still doing the same
kind of work even if you've got this new
mystical terminology that we're using so
if a Gant chart's a useful way to show
how these pieces fit together is make
sure that we have the right outcome when
we're done why not thanks I'm going to
start winding up the the show now it's
gone far too quick um so apologies for
that there's one question I'm going to
sneak in though it's actually one of my
emergency questions in case we got
finished too early but can you provide
some tips for somebody that's got an
ongoing project that loves what we've
spoken about it totally fits their brain
they want to start adopting things where
could they start we can probably both
comment on that I have some
suggestions I would say first if things
aren't going as well as you like and you
think that oh maybe we should do some of
this stuff let's do some root cause
analysis to understand why I'm a big fan
of root cause analysis so we understand
a problem before we start applying a
solution such as you know maybe you say
oh well we we should do use cases okay
well why are you not already getting the
results that you want you know if you if
use cases are the answer what's the
question might be a perfect solution
might not solve your problem
retrospectives Are a good way to start
that activity in the you're going
through a an iterative project you know
retrospective is a typical part of many
agile projects and those should be taken
very seriously using the knowledge from
that the insights to understand what
didn't go as well as we'd like what did
great and let's translate that into
better action on the next iteration so
if you can trace any of the problems or
issues you encountered back to
requirements related factors then you
can consider which of the 20 practices
we talk about or the dozens and dozens
of practices in other books on
requirements engineering and business
analysis pick out which of those you
think might help you solve that problem
but you can actually start doing this
stuff incrementally if you don't have a
complete set of models fine draw a model
for the next piece of the work you have
to do just to both get comfortable with
the technique and to begin enhancing
your skills yeah you could create a
baseline couldn't you and at any point
and then work from there and that was
exactly you know I wanted to add on that
is assess where you are now now you may
be doing a lot of the pieces of the
practices that we talk about but you may
be calling them something else so
understand where you are and then as
Carl mentioned you don't have to do
everything at once and sometimes it can
seem overwhelming to have you know 20
practices that's a lot of things to do
but you don't have to bite off
everything at once you can you know pick
one practice or one model just to
incrementally improve over time thanks
so I think it's a good time now to ask
my usual question at the end of the show
if there was one thing I'll start with
you Carl first if there's one thing
you'd like a software engineer to
remember from this show what would you
like it to be well my bottom line point
is that all project and product teams
have to deal with requirements for the
work they do whatever they call them and
I think if anyone from a a software team
were to look at the 20 practices that
Candice and I recommend in this book
they would realize that virtually all of
them apply to their work so I suggest
that listeners and readers select those
practices starting with you know maybe
just a couple as Candace suggested you
don't have to do them all right away
select the practices that they think
would be most valuable for increasing
the chance of success for reducing risk
or even better reducing current points
of pain and then think about how best to
adapt the practices to suit the nature
and culture of your project team and
organization so I think of the the
practices that I write about and
requirements books that I've done as a
toolkit and you can assemble you know a
package of tools and techniques that are
going to be appropriate for your project
your situation your problems and adapt
them don't necessarily figure they're
going to plug in exactly without a
little thought and considering your your
culture and and uh you know the nature
of the organization but I think if you
go through the list you'll find that
they pretty much all apply and condas
well I think Carl stole mine but I have
another one up on my sleeve
um it goes back to some of the themes of
the book that we talked about early on
which is you know we don't do software
requirements all at once it is that
iterative and circular process that we
are going to go through multiple times
throughout a product or Project's life
cycle so understanding that you're not
going to you know do the analysis once
and you're done and also that change
happens so those two together means that
we're we should always be constantly
learning more about the product or
project that we're working on and be
willing to embrace that change and move
forward with that project thank you was
there anything we missed would have like
to mention well we could both talk about
this stuff for hours and hours but we
only have one hour here so I think we've
done a pretty thorough job thank you so
people can follow you both on LinkedIn
I'll put the links in the show notes is
there any other way you'd like them to
get in touch if they need need to well
through Linkedin or through our our
websites I think you're going to show
some of our websites there as well so
the website for the book is probably the
most valuable place to get started it's
just software rex.com software req.
comom is a a good entry point into all
of this for example we have a a video
series called the one minute analyst
which has got a just a very very concise
highlights of each of these 20 practices
so that's a good starting point as well
but uh we're pretty easy to find online
so Carlin ctis thank you for coming on
the show it's been a real pleasure this
is Gavin Henry for software engineering
radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other epis of SC radio
is licensed under creative comments
license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]